Michael Xieyang Liu

Human-Computer Interaction Institute, School of Computer Science Carnegie Mellon University 5000 Forbes Avenue Pittsburgh, PA 15213

University of Michigan-Shanghai Jiao Tong University Joint Institute, Shanghai, China

RESEARCH FOCUS

My research is at the intersection of Human-computer Interaction (HCI), programming tools, sensemaking, end-user programming, and intelligent user interfaces, where I design and build systems that accelerate online sensemaking for developers and facilitate human-AI interactions for end-users.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Human-Computer Interaction (in progress)	2017 - present
Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, USA	
Thesis: Scaffolding Knowledge Capturing, Structuring, and Reuse during Online Sensemaking	
Advisors: Brad A. Myers, Aniket Kittur	
Committee: Kenneth Holstein (CMU HCII), Daniel M. Russell (Google, Inc.)	
M.S. in Human-Computer Interaction	2017 - 2021
Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, USA	
B.S. in Computer Science	2013 - 2017
University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA	
B.S.E. in Electrical and Computer Engineering	2013 - 2017

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-reviewed Conference Papers

Michael Xieyang Liu, Advait Sarkar, Carina Negreanu, Ben Zorn, Jack Williams, Neil Toronto, Andrew

D. Gordon. "What It Wants Me To Say": Bridging the Abstraction Gap Between End-User Programmers and Code-Generating Large Language Models [Under Review] at ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2023).

Michael Xieyang Liu, Andrew Kuznetsov, Yongsung Kim, Joseph Chee Chang, Aniket Kittur, Brad A.
 C.9 Myers. Wigglite: Low-cost Information Collection and Triage. Proceedings of the 35th Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2022).

Franklin Mingzhe Li, **Michael Xieyang Liu**, Yang Zhang, Patrick Carrington. **Freedom to Choose**:

Understanding Input Modality Preferences of People with Upper-body Motor Impairments for

Activities of Daily Living. Proceedings of the 24th International ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS 2022).

- Michael Xieyang Liu, Aniket Kittur, Brad A. Myers. Crystalline: Lowering the Cost for Developers to
 C.7 Collect and Organize Information for Decision Making. Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human
 Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2022).
- Amber Horvath, **Michael Xieyang Liu**, River Hendriksen, Connor Shannon, Emma Paterson, Kazi Jawad, C.6 Andrew Macvean, Brad A. Myers. **Understanding How Programmers Can Use Annotations on Documentation**. *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2022)*.
- Michael Xieyang Liu, Aniket Kittur, Brad A. Myers. To Reuse or Not To Reuse? A Framework and

 System for Evaluating Summarized Knowledge. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction.
 5, CSCW1, Article 166 (April 2021) (CSCW 2021).
 - **P**Best Paper Award and CMU SCS News Coverage
- Joseph Chee Chang, Yongsung Kim, Victor Miller, **Michael Xieyang Liu**, Brad A. Myers, Aniket Kittur. C.4 **Tabs.do: Task-Centric Browser Tab Management**. Proceedings of the 34th Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2021).
- Michael Xieyang Liu, Jane Hsieh, Nathan Hahn, Angelina Zhou, Emily Deng, Shaun Burley, Cynthia

 Taylor, Aniket Kittur, Brad A. Myers. Unakite: Scaffolding Developers' Decision-Making Using the Web.

 Proceedings of the 32nd Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2019).

 Best Paper Honorable Mention Award
- Jean Y. Song, Stephan J. Lemmer, **Michael Xieyang Liu**, Shiyan Yan, Juho Kim, Jason J. Corso, Walter S. C.2 Lasecki. **Popup: Reconstructing 3D Video Using Particle Filtering to Aggregate Crowd Responses**. *Proceedings of the 24th Annual ACM International Conference on Intelligent UserInterfaces (IUI 2019)*.
- C.1 Yu-Wei Chao, Yunfan Liu, Xieyang Liu, Huayi Zeng, Jia Deng. Learning to Detect Human-Object Interactions. 2018 IEEE Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV 2018).

Workshop Papers & Posters

- Jane Hsieh, Michael Xieyang Liu, Brad A. Myers, Aniket Kittur. An Exploratory Study of Web Foraging W.3 to Understand and Support Programming Decisions. IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages and Human-Centric Computing (VL/HCC 2018).
- W.2 Michael Xieyang Liu, Nathan Hahn, Angelina Zhou, Shaun Burley, Emily Deng, Aniket Kittur, Brad A.

 Myers. UNAKITE: Support Developers for Capturing and Persisting Design Rationales When Solving Problems Using Web Resources. DTSHPS'18 Workshop on Designing Technologies to Support Human Problem Solving, IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages and Human-Centric Computing (VL/HCC 2018).
- Michael Xieyang Liu, Shaun Burley, Emily Deng, Angelina Zhou, Aniket Kittur, Brad A. Myers.
 W.1 Supporting Knowledge Acceleration for Programming from a Sensemaking Perspective. Sensemaking Workshop @ CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2018).

Patent

- Ben Zorn, Carina Negreanu, Advait Sarkar, Andrew Gordon, Jack Williams, **Michael Xieyang Liu**, Neil PT.2 Toronto, Sruti Srinivasa Ragavan. **Generation of Interactive Utterances of Code Tasks**. *US Patent (submitted)*, 2022
- PT.1 Aniket Kittur, Brad A. Myers, **Michael Xieyang Liu**. **Multidirectional Gesturing for OnDisplay Item Identification and/or Further Action Control**. *US Patent PCT/US2022/043604 (submitted)*, 2022

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Microsoft Research, Research Intern

May - Aug. 2022

with Advait Sarkar, Carina Negreanu, Jack Williams, Andy Gordon, Ben Zorn

Designed, built, and evaluated natural language interactions for end-user programmers.

Google, Research Intern

May - Aug. 2020

with Dustin Smith, Todd Kulesza, and Sarah D'Angelo

Conducted qualitative research on Go developers' refactoring practices and engagement with refactoring tools.

Bosch Research, Research Intern

May - Aug. 2019

with Lisa Yu, Wan-Yi Lin, and Alessandro Oltramari

Worked on crowd & AI-powered projects that aim to improve the safety and performance of autonomous vehicles.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant (advised by Brad A. Myers & Aniket Kittur)

2017 - present

Human-Computer Interaction Institute, Carnegie Mellon University

Working on prototype systems that scaffold developers in making decisions using information from various web sources and enable subsequent developers to learn, understand, and reuse those decisions and rationales.

Research Assistant (with Jodi Forlizzi, Roni Rosenfeld & Ryan Tibshirani)

2020 - 2021

Delphi Research Group, Carnegie Mellon University

Working on the visualization team of the COVIDcast system, which displays indicators related to COVID-19 activity level across the U.S. These indicators are derived from a variety of anonymized, aggregated data sources made available by multiple partners, including Facebook, Google, and Quidel. [Press coverage]

Undergraduate Researcher

2016 - 2017

Crowds and Machines Lab, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

Worked on crowd & AI-powered interdisciplinary projects that address novel and promising research questions.

Research Assistant (advised by Jia Deng)

2015 - 2016

Vision & Learning Lab, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

Worked on a computer vision based toolkit that boosts performance on human-object interaction detection by exploiting human-object spatial relations.

SELECTED HONORS, GRANTS, AWARDS & COVERAGE

in Computing Systems (CHI 2023)	eviews, ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors	Nov. 2022
CMU SCS News Coverage on our CSCW Tool To Help Determine When To Reuse Cor	2021 Best Paper : "CMU Researchers Develop ntent"	Nov. 2021
Best Paper Award , 24th ACM Conference of Social Computing (CSCW 2021)	on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and	Oct. 2021
Special Recognitions for Outstanding Re Interface Software and Technology (UIST 20	eviews, 34th Annual ACM Symposium on User 21)	June 2021
CMU News Coverage on COVIDcast: "Ca Maps"	rnegie Mellon Unveils Five Interactive COVID-19	April 2020
Best Paper Honorable Mention Award , 3 Software and Technology (UIST 2019)	2nd Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface	Oct. 2019

SHF: Small: Knowledge Acceleration for Programming (\$500,000 over 3 years), NSF	June 2018
James B. Angell Scholar, 94th Annual Honors Convocation, University of Michigan	March 2017
EECS Scholar Award, 2017 EECS Honors & Awards Reception, University of Michigan	March 2017
Summer Undergraduate Research Experience (SURE) program, University of Michigan	May 2016
Tang-Junyuan Fellowship (Top 2/250, \$50,000), UM-SJTU Joint Institute	July 2015, July 2016
Dean's List, University of Michigan	Dec. 2015, April 2016
Basic Teaching Assistant Certificate , Center for Learning and Teaching, UM-SJTU Joint Institute	Aug. 2015
Dean's List, UM-SJTU Joint Institute	Dec. 2013, Aug. 2014, Dec. 2014, Aug. 2015
Fellowship for Outstanding Academic Performance, Shanghai Jiao Tong University	June 2015
Meritorious Winner (Acceptance: 9%), COMAP Mathematical Contest in Modeling	April 2015

MENTORING

Jane Hsieh 2018 - 2019

Oberlin College Student (Currently a CMU S3D PhD. Candidate)

Studied programmers' web-foraging behaviors. Contributed to the development of the Unakite system.

Emily Deng 2017 - 2018

CMU Master's Student

Designed and carried out interview studies with programmers that probe their programming behaviors and needs.

Shaun Burley 2017 - 2018

CMU Master's Student

Designed and carried out interview studies with programmers that probe their programming behaviors and needs.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant – 05-410/05-610 User-Centered Research & Evaluation	Fall 2020
Human-Computer Interaction Institute, Carnegie Mellon University	
Teaching Assistant – 05-431/05-631 Software Structures for User Interfaces	Fall 2020
Human-Computer Interaction Institute, Carnegie Mellon University	
Teaching Assistant – 05-430/05-630 Programming Usable Interfaces	Fall 2019
Human-Computer Interaction Institute, Carnegie Mellon University	
Instructional Aide – EECS484 Database Management Systems	Winter 2017
University of Michigan, Ann Arbor	
Instructional Aide – EECS484 Database Management Systems	Fall 2016
University of Michigan, Ann Arbor	
Teaching Assistant – Vv255 Multivariate Calculus	Summer 2015
University of Michigan – Shanghai Jiao Tong University Joint Institute	

SERVICE

Academic Service

Associate Chair ACM CHI 2020 Late Breaking Work Track

Conferences: CHI (2019, 2020, 2021, 2022, 2023), CSCW (2019, 2020, 2021, 2022), UIST

(2019, 2020, 2021, 2022), IUI (2020), VAST (2020)

Paper Reviewing Journal: TOCHI (2022)

Special Recognitions for Outstanding Reviews: UIST (2021), CHI (2023)

Departmental & Community Service

Committee Member REU (Research Experience for Undergraduate) Admissions Committee (2021-2022)

Committee Member CMU HCII Faculty Lunch Organization Committee (2019-2020)

Committee Member CMU HCII Ph.D. Student Lounge Committee (2019-2020)

LANGUAGES, TECHNICAL SKILLS & COURSES

Languages English, Chinese (Mandarin) - Native or bilingual proficiency,

German - Limited working proficiency

Programming HTML/Javascript/CSS, Python, SQL, C/C++, Swift, Java, LaTeX, etc. **Web & App Development** React.js, Angular, Redux, Bootstrap, Node.js, PHP, Ionic Framework, etc.

Deep Learning & AI PyTorch, Tensorflow, ml5.js

Courses Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Advanced User Interfaces, Database Management

Systems, Information Security, Web Development

REFERENCES

Brad A. Myers (doctoral advisor)

Professor & HCII Interim Director

Human Computer Interaction Institute, School of Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University

bam@cs.cmu.edu

Aniket (Niki) Kittur (doctoral advisor)

Professor

Human Computer Interaction Institute, School of Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University nkittur@cs.cmu.edu

Ben Zorn

Partner Researcher & Former Co-manager of the Research in Software Engineering (RiSE)

Microsoft Research, Redmond, US

ben.zorn@microsoft.com

Advait Sarkar

Senior Researcher

Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK

advait@microsoft.com

Andy Gordon

Senior Principal Research Manager Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK adg@microsoft.com Carina Negreanu Senior Researcher Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK cnegreanu@microsoft.com